Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 4 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory04
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 October 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Copies of letters from M. de la Vanguyon and Dumas to Jones, à propos of his departure with the squadron for Dunkirk; second furious memorial printed by Sir J[oseph] Y[orke]; advisability of the squadron leaving before Holland weakens. The affair of the unlimited conveys no nearer completion. Mr. Izard at Amsterdam. Vessel being built from there after Mr. Sayre's pattern. Affair of the deserters from the "Serapis."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 1; L.S. 1p.; Lenoir, Jean-Charles-Pierre. Paris
    Acknowledging Franklin's letter and promising to have Mr. Smith carefully watched; will give orders to the police officers to wait on Franklin for certain necessary details.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 1; A.L.S. 1p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    M. Dumas gone to the Hague. The American squadron to be placed on the same footing as the French men-of-war, so that the English spies at the Helder may do as little harm as possible. Desires to see the Danish pay forfeit in American Possessions for their disrespect towards the Colonies of the United States at Bergen and for their adoption of English party.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Marassá, ------. Mareuil
    Desiring news of Báchet de Rochefontaine who embarked for America in 1778 and entered the army with the rank of Major.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Haag, Jean. Boulogne-sur-mer
    Born in Charleston; served on board an American corsair until captured by the English; his arrival in France destitute of everything; begs Franklin to pay his debts and to procure him passage to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779? November 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Only the Expectation of a happier life beyond the grave enables us to bear this one, where we have continually to part with friends. In heaven we shall all meet again, never to be separated. Gives her idea of what heaven will be like.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Oct,1906, 38.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 2; A.L.S. 4p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Glad that Irish patriots are beginning to stir. Desires Franklin's opinion in regard to the situation in Great Britain. Hears that Capt. Conyngham is to be exchanged; attributes this clemency to fear of retaliation. Describes the conduct of the Danes toward America as dirty; despises them too much to feel great anger, but thinks Jones might take some little revenge on them. Begs for any news from "home."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Berger, J. C. de. Münster
    Desires positions for himself and cousin in the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Quotes from M. de Neufville to show the efforts of the English to cause trouble in the American squadron.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Enclosing copies of the permission to land the wounded British prisoners, and of the agreement between the American and English Commodores. [4p.] Necessity of his having a secretary to help him with the work; understands the Messrs. Lee had such aids with far less reason.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Adams, James. "Mill Prison," Plymouth
    In want of the absolute necessaries of life; asks for a small supply of money.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Montgomery, Robert.
    The enclosed Spanish letter is due to Franklin's intervention and shows that he will be left perfectly tranquil for the future.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 November 4?]; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Is happy amongst her kindred and friends, surrounded by the beauties of Nature, but is not wholly contented, as she thinks of her absent friends. Prefers the quiet pleasures of country life to the excitement and pleasures of the city.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Enclosing copy of the Resolution of the States-General on the subject of the Chevalier Yorke's memorial, and also a copy of the Chevalier's new momorial. (6 p. in French.) Attempt made on the life of Paul Jones by the English prisoners. Further proofs of untrustworthiness on the part of Chevalier G[ran]d.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Boyd, William R. Nantes Castile
    Desires to be released from prison; is an American sailor, and wishes to return to his native land.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Pine, Joseph. Angers
    After being released by Capt. Allen and given a passport to England, he fell into the hands of the French and is now in prison; begs for his liberty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Mitchell, George. Brittany
    Wishes to go to America; begs to be released from prison; his father famous for the number of persons he brought to America from London-derry, Ireland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Gaudinay, —, chevalier de. "Grandville"
    Desires to serve in the American army or navy; is in the French service, so desires secrecy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Steuben, Wilhelm Augustine von (Friedrich's father). Cüstrin
    Having seen in the French Gazette that his son was actually in the American service as Inspector-General, he again takes the liberty of enclosing a letter to be forwarded to him.
    (In German, with French translation.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Capellen tot den Pol, Joan Derk van der. Zwolle
    Begs Franklin not to sign his name on the outside of the envelope, as it excites too much curiosity, leading to the last one being opened. Good news from Capt. [J.G.] Diriks.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 8; L.S. 4p.; Wahrendorff and Son. Wismar
    Writes in praise of the peas produced around Wismar. The English purchase great quantities for their marine service and hopes that Franklin will give them commissions for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Encloses bond for the purpose of obtaining a commission and letters of marque for Arthur Kirk, of the schooner "Independence," arrived at Nantes from Baltimore.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 9; A.L.S. 4p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Wishes Franklin's opinion on the sudden change of orders; was just prepared to go into winter quarters with his troops, when to his great surprise, a special courier arrived with orders to be ready to march at a moment's warning; meaning of all this entirely unknown to anyone at Havre; various conjectures as to the project on hand; no orders arrived for the navy. Delicate treatment of Irish affairs necessary.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 November] 9; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Is displeased at not having beard from Franklin. Hopes he will see his error and repent. Her brother invites Franklin's son to spend a few days with them in the country and to go hunting.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Introducing Mr. Smith and Mr. Watts of Virginia, who desire letters to the American agent at Bordeaux. Is still mystified as to the change of orders and awaits with impatience any messenger from Versailles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 11; L.S. 2p.; Dalton, John et al. Coutances
    Six American seamen tell of their escape from Mill Prison in England. Crossed the Channel to France in an open boat. On arrival were arrested and imprisoned, suspected of being Englishmen. Appeal to Franklin to secure their release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Gradelmüller, Hferonymus. Erfurt
    Desires to establish a printing-house in Philadelphia for the benefit of the Germans there; however, can print in any language; wishes his expenses paid; mentions his qualifications for other employment.
    (In German.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 11; 2p.; Gradelmüller, Hferonymus. Erfurt
    Abstract of the same.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 11; A.L.S. 2p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Has tried to prevent the captors of a certain vessel receiving money in England on letters of exchange which fell into their hands. Commodore Jones to sail soon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Austin, Jonathan Loring. Boston
    Has not time before the vessel's departure to inform Franklin of occurrences here; refers him to the Hon. Mr. Adams, who sails by this vessel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Palmer, Joseph. Germantown
    Wrote in August, 1779, by his nephew, Joseph Palmer, passenger on the "Mercury" packet; since then has heard nothing of him or the vessel. His friend, Mr. Adams, sails the next day and will be able to give Franklin all particulars of recent events. Evacuation of Rhode Island by the enemy two weeks before, leaving the town of Newport in a tolerably good condition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Introducing his little grandson, who is to sail for France under Mr. Adams's care, where he will perfect himself in the French language.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 13; A.L.S. 4p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. "Serapis," Texel
    Has been afraid to send evidence against Capt. Landais by post; takes advantage of M. Dumas's kindness to send it now. Is exceedingly sorry for the unavoidable delay in sailing; difficulty of obtaining supplies; embarrassed with more than 500 prisoners; expects to be ready to start in a few days, though he must run the risk of meeting the enemy who are far superior to his whole force. Hopes Franklin will approve his arrangements on board the "Alliance." Men and officers on board the "Bon Homme Richard" in want of everything; afraid to mention this to M. de Chaumont after his unmerited reproaches; has written to Dr. Bancroft on the subject of his misunderstanding with de Chaumont; hopes Franklin approves his attitude.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 13; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Has been away for sixteen days and has not heard from him. Sends compliments of her family. (In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Boyd, William R. Nantes Castile
    Begs Franklin to procure his release from prison; has been in the American navy. Falsely accused of breaking jail and taking money from the Agent. Received three wounds in the American service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 15; L.S. 2p.; Coder, Henry
    Grateful for Franklin's intervention on his brother's behalf; begs him to say a few good words in his favor to M.de. Sartine, that justice may be rendered him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 15; A.L.S. 1p.; d'lvernois, M.F. Geneva
    Franklin's connection with M.de Vergennes fits him above all men to make the truth known. His fellow-citizens have a difficult course to follow, but they have a new model to imitate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 16; A.L.S. 2p.; de Brady, Baron. Tabor
    His brother is a Captain in the American army; wishes to obtain a military position for himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779?] Tuesday [November ?] 16; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Has received Franklin's story of the "Whistle" translated into French by himself. It amused them all very much. Will try in future not to pay too dearly for "the whistle." Has often been deceived by others but has never deceived anyone herself.
    Printed in Proc. An Philos. Soc., XL, 106.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David. London
    The enclosed letter from the Committee of Sick and Hurt (XVI, 109) requires no comment. Arranging details concerning the exchange of prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 16; L.S. 2p.; Sanlecque, Marie Del de. Paris
    Heard that Franklin desired to procure some type; takes the liberty of offering him all that is left of her husband's stock.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Martel, -----. Paris
    Wishes information in regard to the commercial affairs of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Veillard, Geneviève-Elisabeth Belamy (Louis-Guillaume's wife). Dreux
    Appreciates Franklin's desire to have her write to him, though she infinitely prefers talking to him or indeed embracing him, although he has accused her of doing it with a bad grace; in spite of his great knowledge of men and things, accuses him of not understanding a French girl. Reasons why she has not written before; gaieties incident to her cousin's wedding. Expresses the greatest affection for him. Sends messages from her father and mother.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 18; L.S. 1p.; Green, John. Nantes
    Has heard that the "Alliance" is without a Commander; offers his services.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    During his stay in England, was engaged in writing on small-pox and inoculation, also upon electricity and medicine. Believes he could be more useful to the world and to his Royal Mistress, were he allowed to stay where he pleased; England agrees with him and Vienna does not. Visits he paid to Sir John Pringle, Lord Shelburne and Dr. Priestley. Has sent Franklin his book, also two papers on electricity; wishes he could spend the winter in Paris to superintend the translation of his works; expects to pay Franklin a visit very shortly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Conyngham, Gustavus. Amsterdam
    His escape from Mill Prison; harsh treatment he has experienced; desires to retaliate; always ready to serve his country.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, 1,346.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Everything adjusted on board the squadron. Capt. Conyngham's escape from an English prison and his arrival at Amsterdam.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 18; A.L.S. 1p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Encloses letters; has forwarded others to the Texel for M. Dumas. Squadron delayed further.
  - to The American Commissioners, 1779 November 19 to 1780 October 23; L.S. Fra[nci]s Hopkinson. 9p.; The Treasurer of Loans. Philadelphia
    Statement of sets of exchange issued to the States of New Hampshire, Massachusetts Bay, Rhode Island, Connecticut, New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Maryland, Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, and Georgia.
    Has reason to believe that the Continental loan office bills have been counterfeited in New York, but as yet has not seen any of these counterfeits.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Bridgen, Edward "Friend". London
    Directions as to his future address. Motto for medals. Question of the coins; the design, mottoes, emblems, cost, etc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Montgomery, Robert.
    Thanking Franklin for his intercession with the Count d'Aranda on his behalf; encloses a copy of a Spanish letter written by the Governor to the Minister, which acknowledges his justification; offers further proof, in order to eradicate any doubt in Franklin's mind.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 20; L. 3d P. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Sends a letter and memoir, which may prove of use of M. Landais, whose reputation suffers from the accounts in the gazettes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Sayre, Stephen. Amsterdam
    Introducing Captains Hodgson and Grenel, both of whom merit Franklin's assistance. Begs that the promised letter of marque may be sent by the first post.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 22; L.S. 2p.; La Blancherie, Claude-Mammès de Pahin Champlain de. Paris
    Asks Franklin's interest on behalf of the institution which so engrosses him; begs Franklin's presence at the next meeting.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Relating to exchange of prisoners detained at Forton.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 23; L. 2p.; ----, ----
    Relative to the exchange of prisoners at Morlaix.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 23; A.L.S. 1p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Introducing Capt. Moses Grinnell, who had the misfortune lately to fall into the enemy's hands, and begging Franklin to indicate to him the best and speediest passage to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Taylor, Cradock. Aix
    Is informed that a cartel arrived at Marseilles some time ago, which is expected to sail on the 4th or 5th of December; desires Franklin to procure him his liberty before then.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 24; A.L.S. 4p.; Thevart, -----. Beauvais
    Offering to furnish America with cloth of his own manufacture.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Besson, George Leopold. Montbéliard
    Implores Franklin's assistance once again in his miserable situation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 25; A.L.S. 2p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    The resolution taken by the States concerning Capt. Jones and his prizes; it was carried by the nobility and ten voting cities of little importance, but opposed by Amsterdam and five other large cities. Wishes that Jones could have departed before this resolution was carried.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Evans, John. Angers
    Through Franklin's interest hopes to procure a pass to return to England; Sir Edward Newenham and Mr. Green will be his security to obtain an exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Darang,-----, chevalier. Nancy
    Concerning several bills of exchange drawn on Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1779.] November 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Beerenbrock, Dr. Paris
    Desiring to know whether Dr. Ingen Housz has arrived in Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Valmont de Bomare, Jacques-Christophe
    Has not forgotten his kindness in inviting him to Passy but his duties as Director of the Museum of M. le Prince de Condé, keep him at Chantilly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Resolution of November 17th, still refusing to deliver up the prizes to Sir J[oseph] Y[orke]'s second memorial, but ordering the squadron to sail with the first fair wind; protests against this last order by various Dutch towns.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 28; L.S. 1p.; Conti, Louis-François-Joseph de Bourbon, comte de la Marche and prince de. Paris
    Asking for passes for two of his grooms whom he is sending into England to purchase dogs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. "Alliance," Texel
    Forwarded Franklin the required certificates respecting Capt. Landais. Hopes his second interview with the French Ambassador will meet with Franklin's approval. Has one hundred prisoners on board; expects to embrace the first fair wind for L'Orient. His reason for not coming on board the "Alliance" earlier was a feeling of delicacy, Capt. Landais having accused him of using his interest with Franklin to supersede him in the command. His strong desire that the "Serapis" should become the property of America. Only his attachment to his duty prevents his embracing Franklin before leaving Europe. Capt. Conyngham is with him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779.] November 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    His lecture on lightning-rods. Forwarded Franklin a box containing the engravings of birds and the memoirs of his brother. Acknowledging Franklin's courtesy to his relative, M. Stanley; recommending M. Desdonaires to his kind attention.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Still waiting for a fair wind in order that the "Alliance" may set sail. At the request of Commodore Jones, encloses copies of letters relative to his two prizes, taken to Norway. [1 p.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 30; A.L.S. 1p.; de Sanlecque, Veuve. Paris
    Concerning printing and type about which Franklin wrote him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Holker, John. Rouen
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of the 22d ult., and promising to look after the eight boxes, sent from Amsterdam, until further notice; his eagerness to oblige Franklin in every possible way; his wife's great admiration and affection for Franklin; begs him to visit them. Anxious for news of Comte d'Estaing's expedition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779. November]; A.L. in 3d P. 2p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de
    Would not have enough time to translate the "Amiens letter." If he wishes, he could send it to the editor of the Journal, who understands such matters. Encloses a note by M. Turgot. Asks if it is true that New York has been taken.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 November [25?]; A.L.S. 3p.; La Vauguyon, Paul-François de Quélen de Stuer de Caussade, duc de. The Hague
    Has informed Mr. Johnes [Jones] of the King's intentions, as transmitted by M. de Sartine; Mr. Jones's conduct in this affair has been most admirable; all he asks is that his crew shall not lose their share of the prize money and that his prisoners may be exchanged for Americans.